Guide to the Franklin H. Wood papers, 1850-1951 UA.29.03.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Franklin H. Wood papers
circa 1850-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
Wood, Franklin H.
UA.29.03.0004
1.5 Linear Feet 1 document box, 1 conservation box
Collection contains correspondence as well as sermon notes and outlines created by Franklin H. Wood, an itinerant preacher largely active in North Carolina during the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Franklin H. Wood papers were received by the Duke Univeristy Archives as a gift in June 2013.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series: Secondary Source Materials, Correspondence, Sermon Notes and Outlines, and a final catch-all series for other materials.
All correspondence and Secondary Source materials came to the archive in a three ring binder donated by the Wood family. Copies were made of facsimiles, and original materials were placed into archival folders. Original arrangement of the correspondence is presumed to have been lost. The correspondence has been organized by date. A large majority of the sermon outlines and notes were donated to the archive in a saddle bag with portfolio divisions. Sermon notes and outlines in the third series have been preserved in original order as found in the saddlebag portfolio pockets, and all sermon materials found in the binder were placed at the end of the series, as indicated by the folder titles.
Scope and Contents
The collection is primarily composed of correspondence during F.H. Wood's time as chaplain in the confederate army, as well as sermon outlines and notes encompassing his long itinerant preaching career. The correspondence is a varied mix of originals, facsimile copies, and transcriptions. Some of the facsimiles and transcriptions do not have the original present in the collection. Correspondents include his wife and children. Topics of the sermons are widely varied, but follow a standardized pattern of 1-2 readings, hymn book numbers, and 3 point sermons on a topic related to the readings.
The collection also includes secondary source material assembled posthumously by Franklin Wood's family. This includes a memoir, photographs, and an excerpt from a published work.
Biographical note
Rev. Franklin Harris Wood was born in Randolph County, August 19th, 1836, and died at Trinity, October 2nd, 1913. His parents were Peneul and Callista Wood. He was brought up on a farm and in the church, and studied agriculture and the bible, educated by his parents until he went to the county high school. He married Elizabeth Pearce on October 23rd, 1858, and they remained married until his death in 1913.
He was admitted on trial into the North Carolina Methodist Conference at Beaufort, December 14th, 1859. He was ordained deacon at Louisburg, December 8th, 1861, and ordained elder at Greensboro on December 6th, 1863. He was an itinerant minister without break until 1901 when he retired due to deteriorating health. As part of that ministry, he served with the Confederate Army as a chaplain, attached to the North Carolina 22nd Regiment.
Preaching -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Duke University. University Archives; Wood, Franklin H.; Wood, Elizabeth Frances Pearce
- Secondary Source Materials, 1873-1951; 2 folders
  - Secondary Source Material, Photographs, 1873-1951; 6 items
    - Excerpt. Tar Heel Editor by Joseph Daniels, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes on Scrapbook (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Mental Photograph" and accompanying letter, 1873-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photograph (old age), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Portrait reproductions - Elizabeth F.P. Wood, Franklin H. Wood, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photograph (middle age), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Memoir - J.R. Scroggs, 1913 November-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1858-1903; 6 folders
  - Correspondence (facsimile, transcription), Undated; 2 items
    - Petersburg Virginia, Tuesday Night (facsimile, transcription), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (original, facsimile, transcription), 1858-1862; 4 items
    - Greensboro NC, October 13th 1858 (facsimile), 1858 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cape Hatteras, March 21, 1860 (transcription), 1860 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hatteras NC, March 21st, 1862 (facsimile, transcription), 1862 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Richmond VA, June 5th 1862 (original), 1862 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (facsimile, transcription), 1864, March; 3 items
    - March 4th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - March 20th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - March 25th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (original, facsimile, transcription), 1864 May; 3 items
    - May 10th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - May 23rd 1864 (original), 1864 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - May 26th, 1864 (transcription), 1864 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (original, facsimile), 1864 June-November; 8 items
    - June 30th, 1864 (facsimile) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - July 10th, 1864 (original), 1864 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - July 18th, 1864 (original) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - August 30th, 1864 (facsimile) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - September 8th, 1864 (original), 1864 September 8th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - September 30th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - November 7th, 1864 (facsimile), 1864 November 7th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Envelope (facsimile), 1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (original, facsimile), 1880-1903; 2 items
    - May 9th, 1880 (facsimile), 1880 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - December 30th, 1905 (original), 1905 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Sermon Notes and Outlines, between 1850-1910
  - Notes and Outlines of Sermons Delivered by Franklin H. Wood (transcription), 1874; 7 items
    - Notes and Outlines of Sermons Delivered by Franklin H. Wood. (transcription), 1874 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 1), between 1850-1910
    - Luke 18:1, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jude 20, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Paper scraps (3), between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Matthew 6:14,16, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - A General Judgement, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - A Christian's Rest, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Power of Faith, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 2), between 1850-1910; 12 items
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Untitled Leaf, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Matthew 18:11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Untitled Fragment (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ecclesiastes 13:11, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mark 13:37, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hebrews 4:9, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Serving God, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Salvation by Faith Only (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - John 9:25, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hebrews 6:13-20, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Future Dwelling Place of the Lord, 1867 January (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag Pocket 3), between 1850-1910; 9 items
    - The Advent of God into the World, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Ministry - Works and Maintenance, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Seek the Lord, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Proverbs 4:18, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Romans 1:16, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Luke 16:13, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 2 Timothy 4:8, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Untitled Leaf, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 2 Corinthians 12:9-10, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 4), between 1850-1910; 11 items
    - Scripture Notes, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Acts 5:17-42, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Nature and Importace of the Doctrine, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Responsibilites of the Clergy, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Christ the Way, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Existence of God, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - I Corinthians 10:12-19, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Luke 15:2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Christian's Fiery Trials, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 5), between 1850-1910; 3 items
    - Divine Providence, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Rum Traffic, a Stronghold of Sin, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lessons - The Incarnation of Christ: A Sufficient Reason for the Joy of all Peoples, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 6), between 1850-1910
    - Isaiah 42; Luke 2:1-14, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1 Corinthians 6:19-20, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pocket Diary (Saddlebag pocket 7), 1881-1901
    - Pocket Diary, 1881-1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 8), between 1850-1910; 12 items
    - Sermon Notes, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - List and Microbiography of Prominent Methodists, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 119: Psalm 9, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Eternity and Spirituality of God, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Untitled Prayer/Hymn, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Ministerial Support, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - In what Consists the Joys of Heaven (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Judgement of God Concerning the Death of Christ, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Christ's Humanity, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The General Judgement, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Sufferings of Christ, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 9), between 1850-1910; 5.0
    - Lessons 34th Psalm - Goodness of God, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Justification by Faith Only, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Love as a Constraining Influence, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Coming of Christ the World's Necessity, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Acts 1:8, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 10), between 1850-1910; 11 items
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The True Lord, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - How we Show Forth the Death of Christ in the Sacrament, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Religious Education, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Isaiah 57:20, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Baptism - Subjects. Communion., between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - [Title Damaged], between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Extent of the Atonement, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Relation which Christianity Sustains to the World, and is Work., between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - James 1:12, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - There is Remission of Sins, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 11), between 1850-1910; 10 items
    - Why the Church Should Carry the Gospel to all Nations, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Do not Propose to Define Prayer, or Discuss the Duty of its Performance; but its Profit, or Benefit, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Support of the Ministry, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1 Corinthians 13:13, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper subscription recipt, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - That the Salvation of the Soul is the One Supreme Necessity of Man, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1 Corinthians 10:12, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Christian Perfection, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 15 Psalms; Luke 18:9-12, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 12), between 1850-1910
    - Colossians 3:3, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1 Peter 3:18, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Romans 14, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Necessity of the Holy Spirit to Believers, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Sacrament, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 122 Psalms, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Origin and Instrumentality of Man's Salvation, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Assorted Notes, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 84 Psalms, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Saddlebag pocket 13), between 1850-1910; 19 items
    - UNC Commencement/James 1:25, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Matthew 18:11, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Acts 24:25, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Peter 3:18, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ecclesiastes 7:14, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Ancient Landmarks (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Sunday School Sermons, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Sufferings of Christ and the Glory that Shall Follow, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Luke 15:18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Peter 4:12-13, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Instrumental Course of Man's Final Condemnation, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Matthew 26:14-30, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Various Notes, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Mark 12:24/Luke 18:1, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - John 3:16, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Baptism - Mode, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Untitled Fragment, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Titus 3:4-7, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1 Samuel 12:23, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sermon Notes and Outlines (Binder), between 1850-1910; 13 items
    - The Divinity of our Lord, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Unwillingness of our God that any should Perish, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Instrumentality of the Church, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Church - Its Foundations, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - But God Commandeth, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Highest Impression of Human and Divine Love: and the Contrast Between the Two, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Acts 26:28, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Luke 10:3-7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Luke 15:18, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - John 12:35-36, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Condemnation of the Sinner, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Procession. Personality and Duty of the Holy Ghost, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Omnipotence of God, between 1850-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Pocket Books, Envelope, Shipping List, between 1850-1910
  - Envelope, Shipping List, between 1850-1910; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pastor's Pocket Record, 1871-1873; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pastor's Visiting and Memorandum Book, 1879; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Artifacts
  - Saddlebag (Box 2)